<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exposition after the maner of a co[n]templacyon vpon ye .li. psalme, called Miserere mei Deus</title>
            <title>Expositio in psalmos Miserere me Deus. English</title>
            <author>Savonarola, Girolamo, 1452-1498.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1534</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11539</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21789.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106805</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842515</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842515</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7177</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11539)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7177)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 448:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exposition after the maner of a co[n]templacyon vpon ye .li. psalme, called Miserere mei Deus</title>
                  <title>Expositio in psalmos Miserere me Deus. English</title>
                  <author>Savonarola, Girolamo, 1452-1498.</author>
                  <author>Marshall, William, fl. 1535.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In flete strete by John Byddell dwellynge next to Flete brydge at the sygne of our lady of pytye, for wyllyam Marshall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprented at Londo[n] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1534]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by William Marshall (?), of: Savonarola, Girolamo.  Expositio in psalmos Miserere me Deus.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 21795.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 21795 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalm 51 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="exposition">
            <pb facs="tcp:7177:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7177:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ An expoſition after the maner of a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>templacyon vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .li. pſalme called Miſerere mei Deus.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Las wretche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I am / confortleſſe &amp; forſaken of all men / which haue offended both heuen &amp; earth. Whether ſhall I go? or whether ſhall I turne me? To who ſhall I flye for ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coure? Who ſhall haue pytye or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion on me? vnto heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dare I not lifte vp myne eyes / for I haue greuouſly ſynned agaynſt it. And in the earthe can I fynde no place of defence / for I haue bene noyſom vnto it. What ſhall I nowe do? ſhall I deſpayre? God forbyd. full mercyfull is god / and my ſauiour is meke and louyng / therfore only god is my refuge he wyll not deſpyſe his creature neither forſake his owne ymage. Vnto the therfore moſt meke and merciful god come I all ſad and ſorowfull for thou onely art my hope / and thou art onely the toure of my defence. But what ſhall I ſay vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> / ſyth I dare not lyft vp myne eyes? I wyll poure oute the wordes of ſorowe / 
<pb facs="tcp:7177:2"/>I wyll hartelye beſeche the for mercye and wyll ſaye. Haue mercy vpon me (oh god) accordynge to thy greate mercye.</p>
            <p>¶ God whiche dwelleſt in lyghte that no man can attayne / God whiche art hid and canſt not be ſene with bodely eyes / nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended with ony vnderſtondynge that euer was made / nether expreſſed with the tongues of men or angels. My god, the / which art incomprehenſible do I ſeke, the which canſt not be expreſſed do I cal vpon what thinge ſo euer thou art, which art in euery place. I knowe that thou art y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt hye &amp; excellent thyng, yf thou be a thynge / and not rather the cauſe of all thynge, yf I may ſo call the, for I fynde no name by the whiche I maye name or expreſſe thyne in enarrable maieſty. God (I ſaye) whiche art all thynges that are in the, for thou art euen thyne owne wyſdom, thy power and thy moſte gloriouſe felycyte. Seynge ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that thou art mercyful, what art thou but euen the very mercy it ſelfe? And what am I / but very myſerye? Beholde therfore a god whiche art mercye, beholde myſerye is before the, what ſhalt thou do mercye? truely thy worke, canſt thou do otherwyſe then thy nature is? And what is thy worke verely to take awaye myſery, and to lyfte
<pb facs="tcp:7177:2"/>vp them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are in wretched condicyon, ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore haue mercy on me oh god. God I ſaie whiche art mercye take awaye my miſery / take awaye my ſynnes, for they are myne extreme miſerye. Lyfte vp me which am ſo miſerable / ſhew thy worke in me and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyſe thy power vpon me. One depth requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth another, the depthe of myſerye requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the depthe of mercye. The depthe of ſynne axeth the depthe of grace &amp; fauoure. Greater is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> depthe of mercy then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> depth of mſerye. Let therfore the one depth ſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vp the other. Let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> botomleſſe depthe of mercye ſwalow vp the profounde depth of myſerye.</p>
            <p>¶ Haue mercy on me oh god according to thy greate mercye. Not after the mercye of men whiche is but ſmall, but after thyne owne mercy whiche is greate, which is vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meſurable, which is inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſible, which paſſeth all ſynnes without compariſon.</p>
            <p>Accordynge to that thy greate mercy with the whiche thou haſt ſo loued the world, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou woldeſt geue thyne only ſonne. What mercye can be greater? What loue can be more. Who can deſpayre? Who ſhulde not haue good confidence? God was made ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and crucyfied for men. Therfore haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye on me oh God accordynge to this thy
<pb facs="tcp:7177:3"/>greate mercye by the whiche thou haſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thy ſonne for vs, by whiche (throughe hym) thou haſte taken awaye the ſynne of the worlde, by whiche (through his croſſe) thou haſte lyghtened all men, by whiche (through hym) thou haſt redreſſed all thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges in heuen and erth. Waſh me (oh lorde) in his bloude, lyghten me in his humilite / redreſſe me in his reſurreccion. Haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye on me oh god not after thy ſmal mercy for that is but thy ſmall mercy (in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) when thou helpeſt men of theyr bode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly euylles, but it is greate when thou forge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueſt ſynnes, and doſt eleuate men by thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure, aboue the toppe of the erth. Euen ſo Lorde haue mercye on me accordinge to this thy greate mercye, that thou turne me vnto the, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou put out my ſynnes, &amp; that thou iuſtefie me by thy grace &amp; fauoure.</p>
            <p>And accordinge to the multitude of thy compaſſions wype awaye myne iniquite.</p>
            <p>¶ Thy mercy lorde is the habundaunce of thy pytye, by the whiche thou lokeſt gente<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore and wretched. Thy compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions are the workes, and proceſſes of thy mercy. Marie Magdalene came vnto thy fete (good Ieſu) ſhe waſſhed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with her teares &amp; wyped the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with her here, thou for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaueſt her and ſenteſt her awaye in peace,
<pb facs="tcp:7177:3"/>this was (Lorde) one of thy compaſſions. Petre denyed the and forſoke the with an othe / thou lokedſte vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym and he wepte bitterly / thou forgaueſte hym and madeſte hym one of the chyef amonge thyne Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les this was (lorde) a nother of thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. The theſe on the croſſe was ſaued with one worde. Paule in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> furious wod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his perſecution was called and by &amp; by fulfylled with the holy ghoſte, theſe are lorde thy compaſſions. The tyme ſhulde fayle me yf I ſholde numbre all thy merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſions, for loke how many ryght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe men there be, &amp; ſo many at thy godly compaſſions. There is none that can glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye in hym ſelfe. Let them all come that at ryghtwyſe other in erth, or in heauen and let vs axe them before the whether they be ſaued by theyr owne power and vertue.</p>
            <p>And ſurely all they wyll anſwere with one herte and one mouthe ſayenge. Not vnto vs (Lorde) not vnto vs, but vnto thy name geue all the prayſe / for thy mercye and for thy truthes ſake. For they in theyr owne ſwerde poſſeſſed not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lande, &amp; theyr owne arme or power ſaued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not, but thy right hande &amp; thyne arme, &amp; the lyghte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ing of thy cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for thou delytedſte in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is) they are not ſaued for theyr owne deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynges
<pb facs="tcp:7177:4"/>leſt ony man ſhold boſte him ſelfe / but becauſe it pleaſed the ſo to be. whiche thynge the prophet doth alſo more expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye witneſſe of the when he ſayth: he ſaued me becauſe he wolde haue me. Sith ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that thou art the ſame god with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is no alteration or variableneſſe, neyther art thou chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged vnto darkneſſe: and we thy creatures as well as our fathers whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che were borne vnder co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cupiſcence ſynners as well as we / and ſyth there is but one mediator &amp; atonemente betwene god and man that is Chriſt Ieſus which endureth for euer / why doſte thou not poure on thy plentuous compaſſyons vpon vs / as well as thou dideſt vpon our fathers? haſt thou forgoten vs? or are we only ſynners? dyd not Chriſte dye for vs? Are all thy mercies ſpent and none lefte?</p>
            <p>¶ Lorde our god I deſyre and hertely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche the / to put out myne iniquite accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng vnto the multitude of thy compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. For many ye and infinite ar thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions / that accordynge (I ſaye) to the multytude of thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſions thou vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to quench my ſynne: that as thou haſt drawen and receyued i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>numerable ſynners and haſte made them ryghtuous / euen ſo that thou wylte drawe and take me and
<pb facs="tcp:7177:4"/>make me ryghtwyſe throughe thy grace and fauour / therfore accordyng to the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſions wype away myne iniquite. Clenſe and puritie myne herte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> (after all myne iniquite is put out &amp; all my vnclenneſſe clenſed) it maye be as a clene table in the whiche the fynger of god may wryte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of his loue and charite with the whiche can none iniquite continue.</p>
            <p>Yet waſhe me more from myne iniquite and clenſe me from my ſynne.</p>
            <p>¶ I graunte and knowlege oh lorde thou haſt ones put out myne iniquite thou haſt put it out agayne and haſte waſhed me a thouſande tymes / how be it yet waſhe me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> myne iniquite / for I am fallen agayne. Doſte thou vſe to ſpare a ſynfull man vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll a certeyne numbre of his ſynne / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che when Peter enquyred / how often ſhal my brother offende agaynſt me / and I ſhal forgeue hym / whether ſeuen tymes? thou anſweredſte: I ſaye not ſeuen tymes but ſeuentye tymes ſeuen tymes takynge that certeyne nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre / for an infinite nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre. Sith then that a man muſt forgeue ſo ofte ſhalt thou in pardonyng &amp; forgeuenes be paſſed of a man? is not God more then man? is he not better then man? ye rather God is the great lorde &amp; euery man lyuyng is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge
<pb facs="tcp:7177:5"/>thing but all vanite. And only god is good and euery man a lyar, haſt thou not ſayed. In what houre ſo euer the ſynner doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent I wyll not reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre any of his iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? Beholde I a ſynner do repête &amp; morne for myne olde preuy ſores feſtred within, &amp; now at they broken forth for myne owne folyſhneſſe. I am depreſſed and ſore broken I walke in continuall morninge / I am fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and very weake / I roored for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſorowe of myne herte. Lorde all my deſyres are before the and my ſorowfull ſyghes at not vnknowne vnto the. Myne herte tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bleth and panteth for ſorow / my ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth ſayleth me and euen the very ſyghte of myne tyes ceaſe from theyr office. Wherfore then oh lorde doſte thou not put awaye myne ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity? And yf thou put it out accordinge to the multytude of thy mercyes / yet waſhe me from myne iniquite. For yet am I not perfeytly purefyed, funiſhed thy worke, take awaye the hole offence and alſo the payne that is due vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crune, encreate thy lyght with in me. Kendle myne herte with thy loue &amp; cherite put out al feare / for perfayte loue ſendeth awaye feare. Let the loue of the worlde, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of the fleſſhe, the loue of vayne glorye, &amp; the loue of my ſelfe vtterly departe fro me / yet fryll more &amp; more waſh
<pb facs="tcp:7177:5"/>me from myne iniquite by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which I haue offended agaynſt my neighbour, and clenſe me from my ſynne that I haue committed agaynſte god. I wolde haue the put away not only the faute &amp; payne that foloweth it, but alſo the occaſion and nouryſhment of ſynne. Waſhe me I ſaye with the water of thy gracyous fauoure, with water of which he that drinketh ſhall not thyrſt for euer, but it ſhall be made in hym a fontay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of lyuynge water runnynge in to euer laſtynge lyfe. Waſhe me with the comforta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble waters of thy holye ſcriptures that I maye be nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred among them vnto whom thou ſaydeſt. Now are ye clene for my wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des which I haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto you Io. xiij.</p>
            <p>For I knowlege myne inyquyte, and my ſynne is euer before myne iyes.</p>
            <p>¶ Although through the beholding of thy mercy and compaſſions I may be bolde to flye vnto the (oh lorde) yet wyl I not come as the Phariſe whiche prayed not, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ther prayſed hym ſelfe, &amp; deſpiſed his neigh boure, but I come vnto the, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> publican Lu. xviij. which durſt not lyfte vp his iyes vnto Heauen. For I alſo do knowlege myne inyquyte / and whyles I pondre my ſynnes I dare not lyfte vp myne tyes / but humbelynge my ſelfe with the Publicane
<pb facs="tcp:7177:6"/>I ſaye: God be mercyfull to me a ſynner. My ſoule wauereth betwene hope &amp; feare and ſomtyme for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare of my ſynnes (whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che I feale and knowlege to be in me) I am ready to deſpayre / ſomtyme throughe the hope of thy mercy / I am lyfted vp and conforted. Neuertheleſſe becauſe that thy mercy is greater the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my miſery I wyl euer lorde truſte in the and wyll ſynge oute thy plentuous compaſſyons for euer. For I knowe that thou deſyreſt not the deathe of a ſynner / but rather that he were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted and that he wolde knowlege his iniquite and forſake his ſynne / and ſo come to the that he maye lyue.</p>
            <p>¶ My god graunte me that I maye lyue in the / for I knowlege my wyckedneſſe / I knowe what a greuous burthen it is, how copious / &amp; how ieoperdious. I am not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunt of it / I hide it not but ſet it eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore myne eies / that I maye waſhe it with my teares and knowlege vnto the Lorde myne vnryghtwyſneſſe agaynſte my ſelfe. And alſo my ſynne which I haue proudly done agaynſte the / is euer agaynſt me / and therfore it is agaynſte me / becauſe I haue ſinned agaynſt the: &amp; it is truly againſt me / for it is eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt my ſoule / &amp; accuſeth me euer before the my iudge &amp; conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pneth me
<pb facs="tcp:7177:6"/>euer &amp; in euery place: and it is ſo agaynſte me that it is euer before my face and ſton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth but agaynſt me that my prayer maye not perce through vnto the / that it myght take thy mercy fro me &amp; hynder thy mercye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it can not come at me: therfore do I tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and therfore do I morne beſechyng thy mercy. Therfore (oh lorde) as thou haſt gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen this grace vnto me to knowe my wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe and to bewayle my ſynne: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo accomplyſh this thy beneuolence gyuynge me a ꝑfayte fayth / &amp; drawyng me vnto thy ſonne which hath made a ful ſatiſfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for all my ſinnes. Geue me lorde this precious gyfte for euery good gyfte and euery par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feyte gyfte is from aboue comyng from the father of lyght. Agaynſt the only haue I ſynned: &amp; haue done that which is euyll in thy ſight: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou maiſt be iuſtified in thy wordꝭ: &amp; mayſt haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> victorie when thou art iudged. ¶ I haue ouermoch ſinned vnto the alone / for thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundedſt me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I ſholde loue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> for thy ſelfe / &amp; ſhold loue al creatures for thy ſake. But I haue loued a creature more then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> / louynge it euen for it ſelfe. What is ſynne, but to loue a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for it ſelfe? and what is that / but to do agaynſt the? Surely he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loueth a creature for it ſelfe maketh that creature his God.
<pb facs="tcp:7177:7"/>And therfore haue I ſynned agaynſte the onely / for I haue made a creature my god. So haue I caſte the awaye / and haue ben miurious only to the / for I haue not offen ded agaynſte ony creature in that I haue ſet my truſte or confidence in it. For it was not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded me that I ſholde loue ony creature for it ſelfe. Yf thou haddeſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded me that I ſholde haue loued an aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell onely for hym ſelfe / and I had loued mony for it ſelfe / then no doubte I had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended agaynſt the angell. But ſith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou only art to be loued for thy ſelfe (that is to ſay without ony reſpecte other of good or euyll) and euery creature is to be loued in the &amp; for thy ſake. Therfore haue I ſurely offended onely agaynſt the / for I haue lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a creature for it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>¶ But yet haue I worſe done / for I haue ſynned euen i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy ſyght. I was nothig aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to ſynne before thy face. Oh merci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful god / how many ſynnes haue I done in thy ſyght which I wolde in no wyſe haue done before mortal me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / yea y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I wolde not in ony caſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> men ſholde knowe I feared men more then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> / for I was blinde &amp; loued blyndnes / &amp; ſo did I nether ſe nor ones co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidre the. I had only fleſhly eyes / therfore did I only feare and loke on men whiche
<pb facs="tcp:7177:7"/>ar fleſh. But thou lokedſt on al my ſynnes and numbred them / therfore I can nether hyde them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the / nether turne my backe and flye from thy face.</p>
            <p>¶ Whether ſhall I go from thy ſpirite and whether ſhall I flye from thy face? What ſhall I then do? whether ſhall I turne me? whome ſhall I fynde to be my defender? whom I praye you but the my god? who is ſo good? who is ſo ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle? who is ſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfull? for thou paſſeſt without compariſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al creatures in gentleneſſe. It is one of thy chyefeſt propertyes to forgeue and be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull / for throughe mercy and forgeueneſſe thou doſt moſt declare thy almyhgtyneſſe. I graunt lorde that I haue offended only agaynſt the / and haue done that whiche is euyll in thy ſyght. Haue mercy therfore on me &amp; expreſſe thy puyſaunce in me / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou mayſt be iuſtified i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy wordꝭ / for thou haſt ſayde: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou cameſt not to cal y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rightwiſe / but fynners vnto repentaunce. Juſtefie me lorde accordyng to thy wordes: call me / re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue me / and gyue me grace to do true workes of repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. For this cauſe waſt thou crucyfied / deade and buryed. Thou ſaydeſt alſo: John<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iij. whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I am lyfted vp from of the earth / I wyl drawe al vnto my ſelfe / verefie thy wordꝭ, draw me after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> let
<pb facs="tcp:7177:8"/>vs ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne to gether in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſweteneſſe of thyne oyntmentes. Beſydes that thou ſaydeſte: Math. xi. Lome vnto me all ye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> laboure / and are laden, and I wyll caſe you. Loo I come vnto the laden with ſynnes / labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng day and nyght in the ſorow of myne harte refreſh and eaſe me lorde that thou mayſte be iuſtefied and proued true in thy wordes / and mayſte ouercome when thou art iudged / for there are manye that ſaye: he ſhall haue no ſo coure of his god. God hath forſaken hym. Ouercome lorde theſe parſones when thou arte thus iudged of them &amp; forſake me not at any tyme. Gyue me thy mercye and holeſome ſocoure / and then are they vaynqueſhed.</p>
            <p>¶ They ſaye / that thou wylt haue no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye on me / &amp; that thou wylte caſt me clene out of thy fanoure &amp; no more receyue me. thus art thou iudged of men / and thus do men ſpeake of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> / and theſe are theyr deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynacyons / but thou whiche arte meke &amp; merciful haue mercy on me and ouercome theyr iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / ſhewe thy mercy on me and let thy godlye pytye be prayſed in me. Make me a veſſell of thy mercye / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou mayſte be iuſtefied in thy wordes &amp; haue the vyctorye when men do iudge the / for men do iudge the to be firce and inflexible.
<pb facs="tcp:7177:8"/>Ouercome theyr iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with mekenes &amp; beneuolence / ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men may lerne to haue compaſſion on ſynners / and that malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours may be enflamed vnto repentaunce, ſeynge in me / thy pytye and mercye.</p>
            <p>To I was faſſhoned i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyckednes &amp; my mother co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyued me poluted with ſynne.</p>
            <p>¶ Beholde not lorde the greuouſnes of my ſynnes / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidre not the multitude / but loke mercifully on me whiche am thy creature. Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am duſt / &amp; that al fleſhe is as wytherd hay / for lo I am faſſhoned in wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kednes &amp; in ſinne hath my mother co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued me. My naturall mother (I ſay) hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued me of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cupiſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / &amp; in hit am I vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted with originall ſynne. What is origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſynne / but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lacke of originall iuſtice &amp; of the ryght &amp; pure innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy which ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had at his creacyon? therfore a man co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued &amp; borne in ſuche ſynne is hole croked &amp; out of frame. The fleſhe coueteth againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit. Reaſon is ſlender / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyl is weake / man is fraile &amp; like vanitie / his ſences deceiue him, his ymagynacyon fayleth hym his igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce leadeth him out of the ryght way / &amp; he hath infinite i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pedimentꝭ which plucke hym frome goodnes and dryue hym in to euyll. Therfore oryginall ſynne is the rote of all ſynnes &amp; the nurſe of all wickedneſſe.
<pb facs="tcp:7177:9"/>for all be it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in euery man of ſheyr owue nature it is but one ſynne yet in powet it is all ſynnes. Thou ſeiſte therfore Lorde what I am, and of whence I am, for in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynall ſynne (which conteyneth al ſynnes and iniquites in it) am I faſhoned / and in it hath my mother co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaued me, ſyth then I am hole in ſynnes, and enuyroned with ſnares on euery ſide, howe ſhall I eſcape? for what I wolde that do I not / but the euyll that I wolde not that do I. For I finde a nother lawe in my membres rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge agayneſte the lawe of my mynde / and ſubduynge me vnto the lawe of ſynne and deth. Therfore the more frayle and entang led thy godly beneuolêce ſeeth me, ſo much the more let it lyft vp and confort me, who wolde not pytye one y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is ſyke? who wolde not haue compaſſion on hym that is dyſea ſed? Come come ſwete Samaritane &amp; take vp the wounded and halfe deade / cure my woundes / poure in wyne and oyle, ſet me vpon thy beeſt, bringe me into the houry / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytte me vnto the hoſte, take out two pence &amp; ſaye vnto hym, what ſo euer thou ſpendeſt aboue this, when I come agayne I wyll reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. To thou haſt, loued truth / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnknowne &amp; ſecrete tgyngs of thy wyſdome, haſte thou vttered vnto me.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7177:9"/>
¶ Come moſt ſwete Samaritane / for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde thou haſte loued truthe / the truthe (I ſaye) of thy promyſes whiche thou haſt made vnto mankynde / theym haſte thou truly loued: for thou haſte made and kepte them / ſo that thy loue is nothynge els but euen to do good for in thy ſelfe thou art in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uartable &amp; immutable / thou vſeſte not now to loue &amp; anon not to loue (as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do) ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth thy loue ſo come &amp; go. But thou art ſuche a louer as do the neuer chaunge for thy loue is very god. Thy loue therfore wherwith thou loueſt a creature / is to do it good, and whom thou moſt trueſt / to them art thou moſte beneficyall. Therfore what meaneth / that thou loueſt truthe / but that of thy gracious mercy thou makeſt vs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſes / and fulfylleſt them for thy truthes ſake? Thou dydeſt promyſe vnto Abraham a ſonne when he was aged / thou fulfilledſt thy promyſe in olde and ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>reyn Sara / be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou louedſt truth. Thou promiſedſt vnto the chyldren of Iſraell a lande that flowed with milke and honye / and at the laſt dideſt geue it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / for thy truthes ſake.</p>
            <p>¶ Thou madeſt a promyſe to Dauid ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge: I ſhall ſet vp thy ſeate regall one of the frute of thy bodye. and it came euen to paſſe / becauſe thou woldeſt be founde true.
<pb facs="tcp:7177:10"/>There are other iunumerable promyſtes in which thou haſt euer bene faithful becauſe thou louedſt truthe. Thou haſte promyſed to ſynners which wyll come vnto the / for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyueneſſe and fauour / and thou haſt neues defrauded man for thou haſt loued truthe. That vnthryftye Sonne Luce. xv. that toke his iourney in to a farte countre and waſted all his goodes with royatous ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge / when he came to hym ſelfe / he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourned vnto the ſayenge: father I haue ſynned agaynſt heuen and before the / now am I not worthye to be called thy ſonne / make me as one of thy hyred ſeruauntes. When he was yet a greate waye of / thou ſaweſt hym and haddeſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion on him / and ranneſt vnto hym / fallynge vpon his necke and kyſſynge hym / thou broughteſt forth the beſt garment and putteſt a rynge on his finger and ſhowes on his fete / thou kylledſt that fatted calfe and madeſt all the houſe mery ſaieng let vs eate and be mery / for this my ſonne was deade and is alyue agayne / he was loſt and is now founde.</p>
            <p>¶ Why dideſt thou al this lorde god? ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye becauſe thou louedſt truth. Loue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (o father of mercies) this truthe in me / which returne vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a far cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre runne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wardꝭ me &amp; geue me a kys of thi mouth / 
<pb facs="tcp:7177:10"/>geue me thoſe chefe garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tꝭ / draw me i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to thy houſe / kyll y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fatted calfe that all which truſte in the maye reioyce in me / and lette vs eate together in ſpyrytuall feaſtes. On lorde wylte thou exclude me alone &amp; wylte thou not kepe this truth vnto me? yf thou ſhuldeſt loke narowly on our wickedneſſe a lorde: Lorde who myght abyde the? But lorde thou wylte not be ſoo ſtrayte vnto vs / for thou loueſt truth: ye and that with a feruent and incomprehenſyble loue.</p>
            <p>¶ Whiche is the truth that thou ſo loueſt? is it not thy ſonne that ſayde Iohan .xiiij. I am the waye / truth / and lyfe? he is the very truthe of whom all truthe is named in heuen and in earthe / this is it that thou haſte loued and in it only haſte thou dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for thou dydeſte fynde it pure and with out ſpotte and woldeſte that it ſhulde dye for ſynners. Kepe therfore (Oh god) this truthe / beholde I am a greate ſynner in whome thou mayſte kepe it / to whome thou mayſt forgeue many ſynnes / whome thou mayſte purifye in the bloude of thy Chryſte / and whome thou mayſte redeme through his paſſion why (Oh Lorde) haſt thou geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me this knowlege of thi ſonne / and this ſayth of hym? Becauſe I ſholde ſe my redempcyon and not to attayne it that
<pb facs="tcp:7177:11"/>I myght by that meanes be the more vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſorowe? God forbyd. But rather that I maye perceyue the remiſſion of my ſynnes purchaſed by Chriſtes bloude / and ſo by his grace maye obteyne it. Purge me therefore &amp; redeme me oh lorde (for thou haſt vttered vnto me the vnknowne and ſecret poyntes of thy wyſdome) that this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege maye helpe me and brynge me vnto health / for truely the Phyloſophers neuer knewe theſe thyngꝭ they were vnknowne vnto them / yea and vtterly hyd fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. And no man knewe theſe thynges (excepte a fewe whom thou louedſte entyrelye) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy ſonnes incarnacyon.</p>
            <p>¶ The moſte curious ſerchers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde (I meanet the wyſe men of this worlde) lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vp theyr eyes aboue heuen &amp; yet coulde not fynde this thy wyſdom / for thou haſte hyd theſe thynges from the wyſe and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente / and haſte opened them vnto babes / that is / to hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble fyſſhers and thy holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pehtes which alſo haue vittered them vnto vs. And ſo haſt thou vttered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnknowne and ſecrete thynges of thy wyſdom and of thy ſcryptures vnto me / why do I knowe them in vayne? I knowe theym ſurelye in vayne if they profyt me not vnto my helth and ſaluacion. For the philoſophers when
<pb facs="tcp:7177:11"/>they knewe god by his meruelous creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res they gloryfied hym not as god neyther were thankefull / but vexed full of vanities in theyr imaginacyons and theyr folyſſhe hertes were blynded. When they counted them ſelues wyſe / they became toles. Wylt thou ſuffer me lorde to be or theyr numbre? God forbyd. For thou arte euen mercye it ſelfe which doth neuer vtterly forſake any man. Fauoure therefore lorde / fauour and ſpare thy ſeruaunt / and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde hym to be of the numbre of thy babes / that the vnknowne ſecretes of thy wyſdome whiche is an hye / that thou mayſte be prayſed in the worke of thy mercye whiche thou doſte ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercyſe towardes thy ſeruante (Lorde) whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che neuer forſakeſt them that truſte in the.</p>
            <p>Sprynkle me Lorde with yſope and ſo ſhall I be clene / thou ſhalt waſhe me / and then ſhall I be whytter then ſnowe.</p>
            <p>¶ Becauſe lorde that thou haſte loued the truthe and haſte opened vnto me the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne ſecretes of thy wiſdom / I am wel counforted and I truſt that thou wylt not caſt me out of thy fauoure / but thou wylte ſprynkle me with yſope and ſo ſhall I be etenſed. Yſope is a lowe herbe / it is hore
<pb facs="tcp:7177:12"/>and of a good ſauour / whiche ſygnyfyeth nothynge els / but thy onely ſone our lord Ieſu chryſt / which humbled hym ſelf vnto deth: euen vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deth of the croſſe. Which with the hete of his feruent charyte loued vs / and waſhed vs from our ſynnes in his bloude. Which with the redolent ſauoure of his beneuolence and ryghtuouſnes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plenyſhed the hole worlde. Therfore with this yſope ſhalte thou ſpryncle me / when thou poureſte vpon me the vertue of his bloude: when Chryſte thrughe fayth ſhall dwell in me: when thrughe loue I am ioy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned with hym: when I ſhall countrefayte his humylyte and paſſyon / then ſhall I be clenſed frome all myne vnclennes. Then ſhalte thou waſhe me with myne owne teares which flowe out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of chriſt / then ſhall I ſyghe vntyll I be weeye / I ſhall water my bed euery nyght with my teares / ſo that it ſhall ſwymme in them / &amp; then ſhalte thou waſſhe me and I ſhall be whytter then ſnowe.</p>
            <p>Snowe is whyte and colde / but lorde yf thou ſpryncle me with yſope, I ſhall be more whyter then ſnowe / for I ſhall be thrughly endued with thy ſplendent light whiche paſſeth all bodelye wytneſſe. And when I am enflamed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyght I ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:7177:12"/>forſake all my carnall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cupiſcences / colde vnto worldly thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gꝭ / &amp; e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>flamed vnto heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly</p>
            <p>Unto my hearynge ſhalte thou geue ioye and gladnes &amp; my broſed bones ſhall be refreſhed. ¶ Then lorde ſhall I pray vnto the / erly (that is in the begynnyge of thy lyght) ſhalt thou heare my voyce and I ſhal heare what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde god ſhall ſpeake in me for he ſhall ſpeake peace for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and ſhall geue me peace. Lorde thou ſhalte geue me peace for I haue truſted in the / vnto my hearyng ſhalt thou geue ioy and glagdneſſe / When I ſhall heare that confortable wordes that marie herde. And what herde marie (I ſpeake of that marye which ſate at the fere of Jeſus mat .xxvj.) what herde ſhe? Thy fayth hath ſaued the to thy wayes in peace. Let me alſo heare that the theſe herde: this daye ſhalte thou be with me in paradyſe / then ſhall I haue ioye for the remyſſyon of my ſynnes / and gladneſſe for thy bounteous and lyberall promyſes / ſhall I not reioyce and be glad / when thou ſhalt gyue me two folde for all my ſynnes? then ſhall I begynne to taſte how ſwete the lorde is / then ſhall I lerne to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſant in heuenly thigꝭ and ſhall ſaye with the prophete: how great and co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pious is that ſweteneſſe lorde which thom haſte layde vppe for they in that feare the
<pb facs="tcp:7177:13"/>Then ſhall I reioyſe and be glad and my broſed bones ſhall be refreſſhed. What are the bones whiche ſuſtayne the fleſſhe but the powers of oure ſoule and reaſon that bere vp the fraylte of oure fleſſhe that he runne not hedlonge in to all vyces / that a man fall not hole in to vanite and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume awaye? Theſe bones I ſaye are ſore broſed / for the reaſon is very weake / and the wyll is prone &amp; ready to all myſchyef / for euen nowe the fleſhe obeyeth not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon / but reaſon muſte obaye the fleſſhe / ſo that I can not reſiſt vyce / for my bones at broſed. And why are they broſed? for they haue forſaken the / the fountaine of liuyng water / and haue dygged for them ſelues ceſterns full of chynnes whiche can holde no waters / for they are not filled with thy grace withoute whiche no man can lyue well / for without the we can do nothyng. They truſted in theyr owne power which is no power and therfore decayed they in theyr owne folyſſhneſſes. Therfore let thy power come (oh lorde) and then ſhal theſe broſed bones be refreſſhed / let thy grace come &amp; that faith which worketh through loue. Let thy powers and giftes aſſiſt me / and then my broſed bones ſhall be refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed / for my reaſon ſhall be mercy / my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morye
<pb facs="tcp:7177:13"/>glad and my wyll full of ioye. And thus ſhall they all reioyſe / for aboue theyr owne naturall ſtrenghte / when they goo aboute ony good worke they ſhall procede and proſpere well / neither ſhall they leaue it vnperfeyte but through thy helpe ſhall they brynge it to good paſſe and effecte.</p>
            <p>Turne thy face from of my ſynnes and wype awaye all my wyckednes.</p>
            <p>¶ Why lokeſt thou lorde vpon my ſinnes? why nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>breſt thou them? why conſidereſt them ſo dilyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlye? doſte thou not knowe that man is euen as a floure of the felde. why doſte thou not rather loke in the face of thy Chriſte? Alas wretche that I am. why ſe I the angry agaynſt me? I graunt I haue ſynned / howe be it for thy gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe haue mercye on me. Turne thy face from of my ſynnes. Thy face is nothynge but thy knowlege / turne awaye therfore thy knowlege wherwith thou ſceſt &amp; perceyueſt all thynges / but that wherby thou approueſt and diſaloweſt al thinges / wherbye thou aloweſt the workes of the ryghtwyſe and condemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt the reproua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſynnes of the wycked / knowe not my ſynnes on that maner that thou woldeſt impute them vnto me and laye theym to
<pb facs="tcp:7177:14"/>my charge. But rather turne awaye thy face frome my ſynnes that throughe thy mercy they may be quenched / loke lord on the creature whom thou haſte wroughte / loke vpon thine owne ymage / for I poore wrethe haue put vpon me the ymage or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyll (that is ſynne) turne away thy face from the ymage of the deuyll and be not angry with me / and beholde thyne owne image that thou maiſt haue mercy on me. ¶ O mercyfull lorde / remembre that thou lokedſte vpon Zacheum whiche dyd clym vp in to a wylde figge tre to ſe the. Lu .xix. And thou entredſt in to his houſe whiche thou woldeſt neuer haue done if thou had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt loked on the ymage of the deuyll whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che he had put on hym / but becauſe thou ſaweſt thyne owne ymage on hym / thou haddeſt compaſſion on hym &amp; heledſt him. He promyſed to geue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> halfe of his goodꝭ to the poore / and yf he had falſly deceyued ony man to reſtore it foure folde &amp; he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned mercy and healthe. And I bequeth my ſelfe euen hole vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nothynge reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. And promyſe to ſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> for euer with a pure herte &amp; wil fulfil my ꝓmyſe al daies of my lyfe wherfore then Lorde doſt thou not loke in thyne ymage in me alſo? Why doſt thou yet conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> my ſynnes? Turne,
<pb facs="tcp:7177:14"/>I beſeche the thy face fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my ſynnes and wipe away al my wickednes / wype away a: I praye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> that none remayne. For it is wryten he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kepeth the hole lawe &amp; offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in one poynte is gyltye in the hole / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, hath deſetued damonatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / which is the payne of all ſynnes that leade vnto deathe. Put out therfore all my wycked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe / that none offende the / whiche ſholde brynge me to condempnacyon.</p>
            <p>A pure herre create in me oh god &amp; an vpryghte ſpiryte make a newe within me.</p>
            <p>¶ For my herte hath forſaken me &amp; goeth aſtraye vtterly forgettyng his owe helthe: it is wandred in to ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge cuntres &amp; enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vanities / &amp; his eies / are in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vtmuſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes of the worlde. I called it againe / but it aſwerd me not. It is gone / loſt / &amp; ſolde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſinne. what now lord? what ſhal I ſay? A pure hert create i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me go / an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble herte / a curteous herte / a peaceable herte / a ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rie herte / a deuout herte / ſuch an herte as wyl nether do an other ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hurte / nether yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge him ſelfe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is offended / but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do good agaynſt euyl, &amp; ſuche an hert as wyll loue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> aboue all thyng / which wil thinke of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, ſpeke of the, &amp; thanke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. which wyll delyte in hymynes &amp; ſpiritual ſonges and be hole conuerſaunt in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly thyngꝭ
<pb facs="tcp:7177:15"/>Treate this herte in me (oh God) create is of nothyng / that it may be of ſuche effeca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite throughe grace / as nature is neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make it. This grace cometh onely from the in to the ſoule through thy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon / it is the beautye of a pure herte / it draweth vnto him al vertue and expelleth all vyce / therfore create in me Oh god a pure herte through thy grace and make a newe an vpryght ſpirite in my bowels.</p>
            <p>¶ For thy ſpyryte ſhall leade me in to a ryghte waye / whiche ſhall purge me from all erthy affectes and ſhall lyfte me vp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heuenlye thynges. The louer and the thynge that is loued are bothe of one na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. He that loueth bodelye thynges is worldly / but he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loueth ſpirituall thyngꝭ is ſpirituall. Beue me aſpirite that maye loue the and worſhyppe the / the moſt hye ſpirite / for god is a ſpirite and they which worſhyp hym, muſte worſhyp hym in the ſpiryte and verite. Beue me an vpryghte ſpiryte not ſekyng his owne ſpirite profyt and glorye / but the wyll and glorye of god renewe an vpryghte ſpirite within me / re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newe it / for my ſynnes haue quenched the firſt that thou gaueſt me. Beue me nowe a newe ſpiryte that it maye redreſſe that thynge whiche is inueterate / my ſoule is
<pb facs="tcp:7177:15"/>alſo a ſpirite and ſo made of the that of hir ſelfe ſhe is ryghte / for of hir owne nature ſhe loueth the aboue hir ſelfe and deſireth all thynges for thy glory / ſo that hir owne naturall loue is ryght / for it cometh of the but of hir owne frowarde wyl it is inuete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and polluted cauſing hir natural loue to decay. Make newe therfore this ſpirite &amp; this loue through thy grace that it maye walke in the ryght waye accordyng to his nature renue it (I ſaye) that it maye euer enflame me with heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly loue / that it may euer cauſe me to ſighe vnto the / to enbrace the contynually and neuer to forſake the.</p>
            <p>Caſte me not away from thy face / and thy holy ghoſt take not from me.</p>
            <p>¶ Beholde lorde I ſtande before thy face that I maye fynde mercy I ſtonde before thy benigne goodnes lokynge for thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorable aunſwere / caſte me not confuſed frome thy face. who came euer lorde vnto the / and wente away confuſed? who euer deſyred thy fauour / and wente without it. Surelye thou paſſeſte in thy aboundamte pytye bothe the deſeruynges and alſo the deſyres of them that pray vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> / for thou gyueſt more then men can deſyre ye or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtonde when they haue it. It was neuer herde that thou dydeſt caſte awaye frome
<pb facs="tcp:7177:16"/>thy face ony man that euer came vnto th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Shall I oh lorde be the fyrſte that ſhall be caſte away frome thy face and vtterly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded? wylt thou begynne at me to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founde them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> come vnto the? wylt thou neuer more haue mercye and compaſſyon? god forbydde. The woman of canane folo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wed the / ſhe cried and made piteous noyſe ſhe moued the dyſcyples vnto co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſyon / and thou hyldeſt thy peace / ſhe contynued knockynge / ſhe worſhypped the and ſayd: Lorde helpe me / neyther yet woldeſt thou anſwere. Thy dyſcyples entreated for her ſayenge: let her go for ſhe cryeth after vs. But what was thyn anſwer lorde I pray the / what dydſt thou anſwere: forſoothe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſhe wepte in vayne &amp; laboured for nought for thou ſaydſt that thou waſt not ſent but vnto the ſhepe that were peryſhed of the houſe of Iſrael. What ſholde this woman do when ſhe herde theſe wordes? verelye euen dyſpeyre as concernynge the grace y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe requyred: and yet diſpeyred ſhe not / but truſtynge in thy meercye prayed yet agayne ſayenge: Lorde helpe me / vnto whoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunyte (Lorde) thou anſweredſt / it is not good to take the chyldrens breede and caſte it to houndes as thoughe thou ſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt haue geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her a full anſwere and ſayd
<pb facs="tcp:7177:16"/>departe from me / you Canaanites at w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / ye are Idolatres / the precious gyftes of heuenly fauour perteyne not vnto you / I ought not to take them away from the iewes which worſhip tho true and liuyng god / and to geue them to ſuch dogges as ye are whiche worſhyp ydols and deuyls. What ſhalt thou now do thou woman of Canaan? thou mayſte nowe be a ſhamed and gette the away / for the lorde is angry not with the alone / but alſo thy hole na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon. Oh lorde god / who wolde not haue bene co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founde &amp; haue pyked hym away at theſe thy wordes? who wolde not haue mumbled and grudged agaygſt the? who wolde not haue iudged the to be cruell? And yet did this woman contynue ſtyll in prayer. She caſt not away hir confydence / ſhe toke not theſe harde wordes heuelye / ſhe was not angry / but ſhe hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled hir ſelf the more and abode ſtyll in hir petycyon and ſayde with good fyaunce: It is truthe lorde that thou ſayeſt / but I axe no breed / I axe not the fauoure that the chyldrene ſholde haue. I am a lytle whelpe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre the cromes which fal fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the childrens table. Let them floryſhe &amp; aboundde with myracles &amp; other gracioꝰ fauours / but let not me be deſtitute of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of grace, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:7177:17"/>my doughter maye be delyuerd frome the fendes poſſeſſyon for the whelpes do eate of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes which fall from theyr maſters tables / Beholde what faythe / what truſt, and what humylyte was in this woman / therfore thou not dyſpleaſed with her im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate inſtaunce / but reioyſynge in her excellent co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtauncye dydſt ſaye. O woman greate is thy fayth / be it vnto the as thou wylte. Why are theſe thynges wryten lord god? that we may lerne to truſt in the, that we may humbly and deuoutlye contynew in prayer / for thou wylte geue it yf men be greadye. But the kyngdome of heuen ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth vyolence / and they y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> make vyolence vnto it catche it / for what thynges ſo euer are wryten are wryten for our lernynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thrughe patience and confort of the ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures we maye haue hope. Laſte me not therfore lorde from thy face / which ſtonde wepynge and waylynge daye and nyght before thy face / not that thou ſholdeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer me frome the bodelye oppreſſyon of deuylles / but that thou wylte delyuer my ſoule frome his ſpyrytuall power and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynyon. Let me not be ſhamed (O ſwere Ieſu) for in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> onely haue I truſted I haue no helthe nor confort but in the o lorde: for all haue forſaken me / euen my bretherne &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:7177:17"/>childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue caſt me of / &amp; myn own bowels abhorre me. I haue none othee helper / but only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> / Laſt me not therfore away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy face / and take not thy holye ſpirite fro me. There is no man which can ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ieſus is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde but the holy ghoſt / therfore yf I cal vpon the lorde Ieſu / that do I in the holy ghoſte. Yf I be ſorye for my ſynnes whiche are paſſed / yf I are forgyueneſſe / this do I verely by the holy ghoſte. Therfore I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche the take not fro me thy holye ghoſte / but that it maye be with me / and laboure with me / for we wore not what to deſyre as we ought to do. But the ſpirite helpeth our infirmiries and maketh interceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for vs / that is, maketh vs to praye with ſuche ſorowfull groninges as can not be expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with tungue therfore take not awaye this thy holye ſpirite fro me / that he maye teache me to praye / and helpe me in my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure and maye cauſe me to contynue in prayers and reares / that at the lengthe I maye fynde fauoure before thy face / and maye ſerue the all dayes of my lyfe.</p>
            <p>Make me agayne, to reioyſe in thy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge healthe / and ſtrengthen me with a pryncypall ſpirite.</p>
            <p>¶ It is a great thyng that I deſyre o lord / how be it ſith thou art god a great Lorde / 
<pb facs="tcp:7177:18"/>and kynge ouer all goddes / he dothe the iniurie which aſketh ſmal thynges of the. All tranſytory and corruptible thynges at but ſmall in thy ſyghte: but ſpirituall and euerlaſtyng thynges are great &amp; precious. Take away the ſpirite and ſoule from the bodye / and what remayneth but moſt vile dunge / duſte and a vayne ſhadowe? ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore euen ſo muche dyfference there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the ſpirite and the body / as it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the body and his ſhaw we / ſo maye I conclude that he whiche aſketh bodely thynges aſketh but vayne tryfles but he that deſyreth ſpiritual thynges doth ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye deſyre greate thynges / but ſpecallye he that deſyreth thy ſauyng healthe. What is thy ſauynge healthe but Ieſus thy ſonne? whiche is very god and euerlaſtynge lyfe / why ſhall I not then aſke of the this thy ſauyour / ſyth thou art a myghty and moſt lyberall father / whiche gaueſt hym vnto the deathe of the croſſe for me. Nowe ſyth thou haſt ſo offered him for me / why ſhold I be a ſhamed to aſke hym of the? It is a greate and noble preſente, neyther am I worthy to haue ſuche a gyfte / how be it, it becometh thy worthye lyberalite to gyue ſuche noble gyftes / for this therfore thyne ineſtable gentlenes I dare p<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ro;ſume to come
<pb facs="tcp:7177:18"/>boldely vnto the and to deſyre thy ſauyng healthe in whome I myght fully reioyce. ¶ For yf of his carnall father ony ſonne aſke fyſhe / wyll he reache hym a ſerpente? And yf he aſke an egge / wyll he gyue hym a ſcorpion? or if he aſke breed / wil he geue hym a ſtone? Nowe yf carnall fathers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng euell &amp; ſynners / wyll geue vnto theyr chyldre good gyftes whiche they haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued of the: howe moche more thou he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye father whiche of thyne owne ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance arte good / and wylte geue a good ſpirite to them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſyre it of the? Beholde thy ſonne whiche is returned from a farre cuntrey ſorowyng and repentyng / aſketh of the, the fyſhe of faythe / for as the fyſhe lyeth ſecrete vnder the water / euen ſo is faythe of ſuche thynges as are not ſene / he aſketh I ſay a true fayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he may reioyce in thy ſauyng helth: wilt thou reach him a ſerpent? wilt thou geue hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> venome of vnfaythfulnes which procedeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> olde and croked ſerpent y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyl? I deſyre of the o lorde the egge of hope y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as out of an egge we hope for a chyke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſo thrugh hope / that thou wylte graunte me to come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſyghte of thy ſauynge healthe / that oute of my hope maye come this holſome ſyght / as the chycke doth out of the egge.
<pb facs="tcp:7177:19"/>I deſyre the egge of hope / that my ſoule throughe hope maye be ſuſtayned in this vale of teares &amp; may reioyce in thy ſauing helth: wylt thou geue me the ſcorpyon of deſperacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> as a ſcorpyon hath poyſon in the ende of her tayle / ſo I in the laſte ende of my lyfe ſhulde reſerue ſynne / delyrynge my ſelfe and takynge my pleaſure with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> entyſementes of this worlde / whiche ſeme beautyful and flateryng / euen as a ſcorpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth in the face? I deſyre of the alſo (o lorde) the breed of Chriſtes charite by the which he doth comunycate him ſelfe (euen as breed) vnto all men / that I maye euer reioyce in thy ſauynge helthe / wylte thou geue me a ſtone / that is to ſaye hardnes of herte? God forbyd. Why ſhall I then my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt for to deſyre and obteyne great thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the o lorde, ſeynge thou ſturryſt me vp and byddeſt me aſke and knocke / euen tyl I ſeme importunate? And what thyng can I aſke whiche thou ſhalt be better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tente with all / or els that ſholde be more holſome for me then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thou ſholdeſt make me reioyſe in thy ſonne our ſauing helthe? ¶ Now haue I taſted how ſwete the lord is how eaſy and pleaſaunt his burthen is. I remembre what peace and tranquilite of mynde I was in / when I ioyed in god / 
<pb facs="tcp:7177:19"/>and reioyſed in Chriſte my Lorde and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyour / therfore am I now in more ſorow / for I knowe what goodnes and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicye I haue loſte / therfore wyll I crye more importunatlye: Make me againe to reioyſe in thy ſauynge helth / reſtore me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyng which my ſinnes haue loſt. Reſtore me that whiche through my faure is periſſhed in me. Reſtore me (I beſeche the for his ſake that euer is on thy ryghte hande and maketh interceſſion for vs) thy gracyous fauoure / that I maye perceyue that throughe hym thou arte pacefyed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes me that it may be as a ſeale vpon my herte / and that I maye ſaye with the Apoſtle Paule Galath .ij. I am crucyfyed with Chriſt / I liue verely / yet now not I / but Chriſte lyueth in me. But becauſe my frailtye is greate / ſtrength me with a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cypall ſpirite that no troubles or afflycti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons maye ſeperate me frome Chriſte that no feare maye cauſe me to renye the / and that no paynes maye make me flyde from the. My ſtrengt is not ſuffycyent to reſiſt and fyghte with that olde ſerpent and to preuayle agaynſt hym. Peter hath taught me how great our infyrmitye is / he ſaw y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> with his bodely iyes (Lord Ieſu) and was moſte famylyarlye conuerſaunt with the
<pb facs="tcp:7177:20"/>he taſted of thy glorye in the mountayne / when thou waſt tranſfigured: he herde the fathers voyce: he ſawe thy manyfolde and wondrous workes / yea and throughe thy power dyd hym ſelfe manye myracles. He walked on his feate vpon the waters / and herde dayly thy mighty &amp; ſwete wordes: he thought hym ſelfe moſt feruent &amp; hote in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith &amp; ſayde that he was ready to go with the both in to preſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; vnto very death. And when thou toldeſt hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſholdeſt denye the he beleued the not: he truſted in his owne ſtrenght / and truſted more vnto him ſelfe beynge but a man / then vnto the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge very god. But when the hande may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſayde vnto hym. Thou art of the ſame companye / he was afrayde by and by and denied it. There came an other mayde and ſayde: Surcly thou art of the ſame folke: And he denyed the agayne.</p>
            <p>¶ He coude not ſtonde before wemen, how ſhoulde he then haue ſtonde before kynges and tyrauntes? And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was yet ones more enquyred of the by ſtanders and was accuſed to be one of his diſyples / he began to curſe &amp; to ſwere that he knewe the not / what thynke you he ſayde I ſuppoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſware by god and by the lawe of Moyſes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he knewe the not / addynge ſuch wordes.
<pb facs="tcp:7177:20"/>Thynke you that I am the diſciple of this Samaritane whiche / deceyueth the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple whiche is inſpyred with the deuyl / and deſtroyeth our lawe? I am the diſcyple of Moyſes / and knowe not from whence this felowe is. Blyſſed be God that they ceaſed enquiryng any further / for els wold he neuer haue ceaſed denyenge the / ſo that a thouſande interogacyons wolde haue made a thouſande flatte negations: yea a thouſande curſes and periuryes / yet were theſe interogations but wordes. What wolde he haue done (I praye the) yf they had ſcourged hym and buffeted hym well? Trulye he wolde haue ſought and proued all meanes / denyenge / for ſwerynge / cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng and blaſphemyng vntyll that he had eſcaped their handes. But thou moſt meke Lorde lokedſt backe vpon him &amp; by and by he knowleged his offence: Neyther yet durſte he leape in to the myddes of they in and confeſſe the to be the ſonne of God / for he was not yet ſtrengthed with power frome aboue / ſo that withoute doubte he wolde haue denyed the agayne yf he had ſene ony ieoperdye at bande / therfore as it was woſte mete for hym / he went forth &amp; wepte bytterly. But thou after thi reſurre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> appearedſt vnto hym &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortedſt hym
<pb facs="tcp:7177:21"/>&amp; yet hyd he hym ſelfe for feare of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iewes? he ſawe the ſo gloryouſly aſcendyng vnto heuen and was ſtrengthed by the ſyghte &amp; and comfort of angelles / and yet durſte he not go abrode / for he had learned by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience to knowe his owne fragylite &amp; had proued his weakeneſſe. Therfore dyd he tarye and wayte for the holy ghoſt whiche was promiſed. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was come and had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uled Peters herte with grace / then ſiep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e he forthe: then began he to ſpeke / and then with great power &amp; ſignes bare he witnes of thy reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> feared he neyther the hye preeſtes nether yet kynges / but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyſed in tribulacions &amp; receiued the croſſe with all myrthe and gladnes. Therfore ſtrengthen me lorde with a principal ſpirit that I may contynually reioyce in thy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng helthe / or els can I not beare ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye aſſautes agaynſt me. The fleſhe coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth contrarye to the ſpirite. The worlde aſſayleth me on euery ſyde. The deuyl ſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth not. Geue me the ſtrenghte of thy ſpirite y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there maye fall by my ſyde a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande and tenne thouſande by my ryghte hande that I maye be a ſure and ſtronge witneſſe of thy faythe / for yf Peter whom thou enduedſte with ſo manye fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble gyftes / dyd fall ſo wretchelye / what
<pb facs="tcp:7177:21"/>ſhulde I do lorde which haue nether ſene thy naturall preſens: nether haue taſtede of thy glory in the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayne: nether haue ſene thy gracyous myracles: yea and haue ſcarſely perceiued thy meruelous workes / and haue neuer herde thy voyce / but haue bene euer ſubdued vnder<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſynne therfore ſtrength me with a pryncypall ſpirite that I maye perſeuer / in thy ſcruyce and geue my lyfe for thy ſake.</p>
            <p>I wil inſtructe the wycked that they may knowe thy wayes: and the vngodly ſhall be conuerted vnto the.</p>
            <p>Aſcribe not this oh Lorde vnto preſumſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / yf I go aboute to teache the vngodly thy wayes for I deſyre not to teache them as I nowe am wycked / vngodlye and vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bondes of ſyfie / but yf thou make me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne to reioyce in thy ſauyng healthe: yf thou ſtrengthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me with a prynecip al ſpirits and yf alſo thou ſette me free / then ſhall I teach the vngodlye thy wayes. Neither is this harde vnto the / whiche of very ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes canſt rayſe vp chldren vnto Abraham / neither can my ſynnes be impediment vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the yf thou wylte do this / but rather where ſynne is ſo aboundaunte / there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundeth grace Paule yet brethynge out threatnynges and ſlaughter agayyſte the
<pb facs="tcp:7177:22"/>dyſcyples of the lorde receyued co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myſſyon that yf he founde ony whether thy were men or women whiche folowed the &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed thy fayth / he ſholde brynge them pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoners to Hieruſalem. And forthe was he goynge lyke a mad harebrayn and as a ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenyng wolfe / for to ſtray a brode / rauyſh and kyll thy ſhepe. But whylles he was yet in his iourney euen in the heate of his perſecucion / and in actuall doynge of his fynne / whyles he was perſecuting the and wolde haue ſlayne thy choſen / hauyng no maner of preparatyue vnto grace / neyther yet knowlege of his ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e / when with hert and wyl he was thyne aduerſarte / blaſphe med and curſed the. Beholde the voyce of thy mercyable pytye vnto hi ſayeng: ſaule ſaule why perſcuteſte me? by the whiche voyce he was immedyatlye bothe layed a longe and rayſed vp: he was layde a longe and ouerthrowne as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng his body / but he was tayſed vp with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mynnd / thou rayſedſte hym vp that was in the ſlepe of darke ignorauncie and pouredſt in thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous lyght in thoſe yets which were op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with this blynde ſleape: thou ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wedſt hun thy fauourable face and endued hym with thy gracious mercy. Then was he reyfed as it had bene frome dethe / he
<pb facs="tcp:7177:22"/>opened his yeis / he ſawe the and ſayd: lord what wylt thou that I do? &amp; after dydeſt thou ſend a ſhepe to this wolfe / for thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeſt Ananias to go vnto him: And then was he baptyſed and anone was he replenyſhed with the holy ghoſt / and was made a choſen veſſel to beare thy name be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore kinges / natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; the chylder of Iſrael. And without delaye he entred in to the ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagoges and preached thy name ſtoutlye / affyrmynge that thou arte chryſte / He dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputed / preuayled and confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Jues. Beholde lorde euen ſtreyght of a perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toure / thou madeſt hym a preacher &amp; ſuche a preacher that laboured more then all the other Appoſtles. O how greate is thy po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>were / yf thou wylt of a wycked man make a ryghtwyſe / or of a ꝑſecurtoure a preacher / who ſhal forbyd the? Who ſhall ryſyſt the? who maye ſaye vnto the, why doeſt thou ſo? All thingꝭ that thou woldeſt haue thou made in heuen and in erthe / in the ſee and in all bottomleſſe depth. Therfore impute it not to arrogancye yf I coueyte thrughe thy power and not thrugh myne owne to teche the wycked thy wayes / for I know that I can offre nothynge whiche can be ſo acceptable in thy godly ſyghte / this is the moſt pleaſaunt ſacryfyce / &amp; alſo for my
<pb facs="tcp:7177:23"/>for my ſinguler profit / now if thou chafige me in to an other man / then will I teache the wycked thy wayes / not the wayes of Plato and Ariſtole / not the intricate and ſotle propoſicyons of mannes wytte / not the iuſtructions of phyloſophye / not the paynted wordes and vayne coulours of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rethorycans. Not worldly maters and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licyes / not vnfrutfull wayes of vanue / not wayes that leade men in to deathe: But thy wayes and thy preceptes whiche lead vnto lyfe / nether wyll I teache them only one waye but many wayes for manye are thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes / how be it all theſe wayes ende in one / that is in loue &amp; cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte / whiche doth ſo combynde the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hertes / that they haue one mynde and one wyll in god. Or elles maye we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtonde by thy many waies / the dyuers ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of liuyng / wherin euery man walketh accordyng to his vocacyon: ſome maryed / ſome lyuynge chaſte in wedowhod / ſome vyrgyns and ſo forth / theſe walke after dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſe wayes in to theyr heuenlye inhery<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taunce he may beſt ſubdue his rebellyous me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres. Thus wyll I teache the wycked thy wayes accordyng to theyr capacite and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicyon: And the vngodly ſhall be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted
<pb facs="tcp:7177:23"/>vnto the / for I wyll preache vnto theym not my ſelfe / but Chriſt crucified: and they ſhal be conuerted not vnto my prayſe / but vnto the / geuyng the all honour &amp; prayſe / they ſhal leaue theyr owne wayes &amp; come vnto thyne / that they may walke in them and ſo conſequently attayne vnto the.</p>
            <p>Delyuer me frome bloudes (oh god) the god of my helthe / and my tongue ſhal try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphe vpon thy ryghtwyſnes.</p>
            <p>¶ I am ſtyfled in moch bloude / and from the depth of it ſhall I crye vnto the lorde / Lorde herken vnto my voyce. Tarye not lorde for I am euen at the verye poynte of deathe / this bloude that I ſpeake of ar my ſynnes / for as the bodelye lyfe conſyſteth in bloude / euen ſo is the lyfe of a ſynner in his ſynne: poure out the bloude / and the beaſte dyeth: poure out the ſynne know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legynge it vnto god / and the ſynner dyeth and is made ryghtwyſe. Neyther am I wrapped in bloude / but ouerwhelmed and drowned in bloudes / ful ſtremes of bloud<g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g> do dryue me in to hell / helpe me lorde leſſe I peryſhe. Oh God whiche gouerneſt all thynges / whiche onely canſt delyuer me / in whoſe hande is the ſpirite of al lyfe / ryd and purge me from theſe bloudes. Deliuer me from bloudes (Oh God) the auctor of
<pb facs="tcp:7177:24"/>my healthe / God in whome onelye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyſteth my ſaluacyon. Delyuer me Lorde / as thou delyueredſt Noe from the waters of the floude. Delyuer me as thou dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueredſt Lothe frome the fyer of Sodom. Delyuer me as thou delyueredſt the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael frome the depthe of the red ſee / delyuer me as thou delyuerdſt Ionas fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bely of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whale / deliuer me as thou delyueredſt the thre chyldren from the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of burnyng fyer. Delyuer me as thou delyueredſt Peter frome the peryll of the ſee. Delyuer me as thou deliueredſt Paule from the depthe of the ſee. Delyuer me as thou haſt delyuered infinyte ſynners from the power of deathe and from the gates of hell. And then ſhall my tongue tryumphe thy ryghtwyſnes / that is, for thy ryght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſnes whiche I ſhall feale ane perceyue in me through thy gracyous fauoure. For thy ryghtwyſnes (as thapoſtle ſay the Ro. iij.) cometh by the faythe of Ieſus Chriſte vnto all and vpon all them that beleue in hym / then ſhall my tongue tryumphe in prayſyng this thy ryghtwyſnes / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge thy fauoure / magnifieng thy pyty / knowlegynge my ſynnes / that thy mercye may be declared in me which wold vouch ſafe to iuſtefye ſuche a greate ſynner / and
<pb facs="tcp:7177:24"/>that all men may knowe that thou ſaueſt them whiche truſte in the and delyuereſt them from extreme anguyſſhe and aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite o lorde our god. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> Lorde ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou my lippes: and then my mouth ſhal ſhewe forthe thy prayſe. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> ¶ Thy prayſe is a great thynge o lorde / for it proceadeth out of thy fountayne wherof no ſynner dryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. It is no glorious prayſe that cometh of a ſynners mouthe / delyuer me therfore fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bloude (oh lorde) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god of my helthe &amp; my tongue ſhall magnifie thy ryghtwyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And then ſhalte thou lorde open my lyppes &amp; my mouth ſhal ſhewe forthe thy prayſe / for thou haſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kaye of Dauid whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſhetteſt &amp; no man openeth / &amp; openeſt &amp; no man ſhetteth / therfore open thou my lyppes as thou openeſt the mouthes of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantes &amp; ſucktlynges / out of whoſe mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes thou haſt ſtabliſſhed thi praiſe. Theſe truely were thy Prophetes / Apoſtels and other ſaintes which haue praiſed the with a ſyngle and pure herte and mouth / &amp; not the Philoſophers &amp; oratours which haue ſayde / we wyll magnyfie our tongue / our lyppes be in our owne power / who is our god? They opened theyr owne mouthes / &amp; thou openedſt them not / neither yet ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyſſhed thy prayſe out of thyr mouthes.
<pb facs="tcp:7177:25"/>Thy infauntes lorde prayſed the and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues: The phyloſophers went aboute to prayſe them ſelues and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye theyr owne name. Thy ſuckelynges ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tolied thy fame &amp; glorye which they knew throughe heuenlye fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oure. The philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers knowyng the only by natural crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures / coulde neuer perfeytlye exproue thy renowne. Thy ſayntꝭ magnified the with theyr hert / mouth and good workes. The philoſophers only with wordes and their own ſotle imaginations, thy chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue ſpred thy glorie throughout all the world: The philoſophers haue inſtruct but a few of theyr own adherentꝭ. Thy fredes wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h ſpredyng thy glorye haue conuerted innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable men from ſynne vnto vertue and vnto true felicyte: The Philoſophers ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knewe true vertues neither yet true felycyte. Thy welbeloued haue preached openlye thy bounteous gentlenes &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyable fauoure / whiche thou ſhewedſt in thy deare ſonne vnto all the worlde. But the philoſophers coulde neuer attayne to knowe it. Therfore out of the mouthe of infauntes and ſuckelynges haſte thou ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyſſhed thy praiſe / for it haue euer pleaſed the to exalte the humble and brynge lowe the proude / now ſeynge thou doſt euer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſte
<pb facs="tcp:7177:25"/>fyſt the proude / geue me true humilite that thou mayſte ſtablyſſhe thy prayſe by my mouthe. Geue me a chyldes herte / for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepre I turne backe &amp; become as a chylde I can not entre in to the kyngdome of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen / make me as one of thy infauntes or ſuckelynges / that I maye euer hange on the teates of thy wyſdome for thy teates are better then wyne / and thy wyſdome better then all rycheſſe / ſo that nothynge can be compared vnto it / for it is to me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an infinite treaſure whiche they that vſe are made pertetakers of the frendſhyp of god / therfore yf thou make me a childe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalt thou ſtablyſhe thy prayſe in my mouthe. for then ſhalte thou open my lyppes &amp; my mouth ſhall ſhewe forth thy prayſe &amp; ſhall ꝑfeytly declare it euen as thou haſt publy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed it by the mouth of thyne infantꝭ and ſuckelinges. Yf thou hadſt deſyred ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices I had ſurely offered them but thou de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyghtedſt nor in brente ſacryfices.</p>
            <p>¶ My mouth lorde ſhall ſhewe forth thy gloryous fame / for I knowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> this thyng is moſt acceptable vnto the ſith thou ſaieſt by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet Pſal .xlix. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrifice of prayſe ſhall glorifie me / &amp; by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meanes ſhall I be entiſed to ſhew him my ſauing helth / ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wyll I offer prayſe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> praiſe of infauntes &amp; ſuckelynges for my ſymies.
<pb facs="tcp:7177:26"/>And why ſhall I offer for my ſynnes ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther praiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſacryfice? for if thou haddeſt deſyred ſacryfices I had ſurely offed them / but thou delyghteſt not in brente ſacryfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces / canſt thou be pacefied with the bloude of calues or gootꝭ? wilt thou eate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhe of bulles / or drynke the bloude of gootes? Other doſt thou deſyre golde whiche poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeſt heuen and earthe? other wylt thou that I ſacryfice my body vnto the whiche deſyreſt not the deathe of a ſynner / but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that he were conuerted and lyue?</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe I wyll chaſten my fleſhe in a meaſure that through thy grace it maye be ſubdued vnto reaſon and obey it / for in this poynt alſo yf I paſſe meaſure &amp; bryng my body ſo lowe that it is vn apte to ſerue my neyghboure and to do that office whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is apoynted me of god / it ſhall be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted vnto me for ſynne. Let your ſeruing of god be reſonable ſayth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtle Ro. xij. And thou haſte ſayde alſo by the prophete I require mercy and not ſacrifice Oſee. vi. Therfore ſhal my mouthe ſhewe forth thy prayſe / for this oblacion doth honour the / and ſheweth vs the way vnto thy ſauyng helth. My herte is ready (oh god) my hert is readye / it is ready through thy grace to do all thynges whiche are pleaſaunt vnto the: this one thynge haue I founde moſt
<pb facs="tcp:7177:26"/>acceptable vnto the / that wyl I offer vnto the / that ſhall euer be in my herte / on that ſhall my lyppes euer be harpynge / yf thou haddeſt deſyred a bodely ſacryfyce I wolde ſurely haue geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it the / for my herte is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye through thy grace to fulfyll thy wyll: but in ſuche brente ſacryfyce haſte thou no delyght / thou madeſt the body for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit / therfore ſeakeſt thou ſpirituall thyngꝭ and not bodelye / for thou ſayſte in a certeyne place Prouerb .xxiij. My ſonne geue thine herte vnto me / this is the herte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pleaſeth the. Let vs offer vnto the an herte repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge with ſorow of our fynnes and enfla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med with the loue of heuenlye thyngꝭ and then wylte thou deſyre no more / for with ſuche a ſacryfyce wylte thou be content.</p>
            <p>A ſacryfyce to god is a broken ſpyryte: a contrite and humble herte thou ſhalte not deſpyſe (oh god)</p>
            <p>¶ A broken ſpirite and not broken fleſhe pleaſeth the (o Lorde) for the fleſhe is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and vexed becauſe he hath not the car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nall thynges that he deſyreth / or els fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in hym ſelfe ſuche thynges as he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth. But the ſpyrite is broken and vnquy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eted for his faute / becauſe he hath offended agaynſt god whom he loueth. He ſorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he hathe ſynned agaynſte his maker &amp; redeemer / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath deſpyſed his bloude / 
<pb facs="tcp:7177:27"/>that he hathe not regarded ſuche a good &amp; louynge father: this broken &amp; ſorowynge ſpryte is vnto the a ſacryfyce of moſt ſwete ſauoure whiche notwithſtondynge hathe his confeccyon of moſt bytter ſpyces / euen of the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of our ſynnes, for why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les our ſynnes are gathered togyther in to the morter of the herte / and beaten with the peſtle of conpunccyon / and made in to poudre and watered with teares / therof is made an oyntemente and ſacryfyce mooſt ſwete which redolent offrynge thou wylt not deſpyſe / for thou wylt not deſpyſe a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tryte and humble herte. Therfore he that breaketh his ſtonye herte whiche is made with the moſt harde ſtones of ſynne / that he maye therof prepare an oyntmente of repentaunce in abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>daunce of teares / not deſpayrynge of the multytude and gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſnes of his ſynnes / but humblye offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge this ſacryfyce vnto the: he ſhall in no wyſe be deſpyſed of the / for a broken &amp; humble her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wylt thou not deſpiſe oh god. Marye magdalyn whiche was a notable ſynner made ſuche an oyntment: and put it in the allablaſter bore of her herte: ſhe feared not to entre i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Phareſees houſe, ſhe humbled her ſelfe flat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e before thy fete / ſhe was not a ſhamed to wepe at thy mele tyde / ſhe coulde not ſpeake for inwarde ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe
<pb facs="tcp:7177:27"/>/ but her herte melted in to teares / with the whiche ſhe waſhed thy fete / ſhe wypyd them with her here immedyatlye / ye &amp; anoynted theym with oyntment and ceaſed not kyſſynge them. Who euer ſawe ſuche another thyng? ye or who hath euer herde of a thynge lyke vnto this? Surely her ſacryfyce pleaſed the well, and was ſo acceptable that thou prefarredſt it aboue the Phariſe which in his owne ſyght was ryghtwyſe / for it may be gathered of thy wordes. Luce .vij. that there was ſo moch dyfference betwen the ryghtwyſnes of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye &amp; the phareſee as there was dyfference betwene theſe: to waſhe the fete with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter / &amp; to waſhe them with teares: to kyſſe one on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> face / and not to ceaſe to kyſſe the feete: to anoynt the hed with oyle / and to anoynt the fete: with moſt precyous oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: ye moche more precelled ſhe the pha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſee / for he neyther gaue the water / kyſſe nor oyle. O grete is thy power Lord / grete is thy myght which declareth it ſelfe moſt cheeflye in ſparynge and hauynge com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſyon. Now ſe I well that a contryte &amp; meke herte thou ſhalt not deſpyſe oh lord. And therfore endeuoure I my ſelfe to offre ſuche an herte vnto y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>. Nether is it ynough that I ſaye ſo outwardely / for thou arte a god whiche ſearcheſt our hertes &amp; raynes.
<pb facs="tcp:7177:28"/>Accepte therfore this my ſacryfyce: and yf it be vnperfyte / amende thou the defaulte which onely arte of power that to do: that it may be a brent ſacryfyce / all hole enfla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with the heate of thy bounteous che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte that it may be acceptable vnto the / or at the leeſt that thou deſpyſe it not / for yf thou deſpyſe it not / I knowe well that I ſhall fynde fauoure before the, and then ſhall none of thy ſayntes other in heauen or erthe deſpyſe me.</p>
            <p>Deale gentlye of thy fauourable beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence with ſyon, Let the walles of Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem be bylte agayne.</p>
            <p>¶ Becauſe it is wreten Pſalm .xviij. vnto the holy man thou ſhalte be holy / &amp; with the innocen ſhalte thou deale innocenlye, with the pure and choſen ſhalte thou doo purelye / and with the wycked ſhalte thou playe ouertwarte: I am verye deſyrous y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> all men were ſaued / and that they ſholde come vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledge of the truth: which thynge were very neceſſarye for them and alſo for my profyte / for by theyr prayers, ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ortations and examples I myght ryſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this fylthye ſynne and be prouoked daylye to procede vnto better. I beſeche the ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Oh Lorde althoughe I be a ſynner / 
<pb facs="tcp:7177:28"/>that thou of thy fauourable beneuolence woldeſt deale gentlye with ſyon: that the walles of Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> myght be bilt agayn. Syon is thy chyrche / for ſyon by interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacyon ſygnyfyeth a tootehyll / or a place where a man maye ſe farre aboute hym. And euen ſo thy chyrche thrughe the grace of the holy ghoſte beholdeth a farre of the glorye of god accordynge to the capacyte of this lyfe / and therfore ſayed the apoſtle. ij. Corynth .iij. all we with an vncouered face beholdyng as in a glaſſe the glorye of the lorde / after the ſame ymage ar tranſfor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med from glorye to glorye as by the ſprete of the lorde.</p>
            <p>Lorde god howe ſmall is thy Chyrche at this daye? almoſt the hole worlde is fallen frome the, for there are manye mo myſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auntes then chryſten / and yet amonge the chryſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> how many are there which forſake worldly thynges and ſeke the glory of the lorde? ſurely ye ſhall fynde very fewe, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paryſon of theym whiche are addycte to worldye thynges / whoſe god is thyr belye and glorye to theyr ſhame and confuſyon. Deale gentelye Lorde of thy fauourable beneuolence with Syon: that it maye be encreaſed bothe in multytude and alſo in good lyuyng. Beholde frome heauen and deale gentelye as thou arte wonte to do:
<pb facs="tcp:7177:29"/>that thou wylte ſende amonge vs the fyer of thy charyte / whiche maye conſume all our ſynnes. Deale lorde accordynge to thy fauourable beneuolence / and do not with vs after our deſeruyng / nether yelde thou vs againe according to our iniquities / but ordre vs accordynge to thy greate mercye. Thou art Lorde our father and redemer / thou art our hope and euerlaſtyng helche. Euery man deſyreth goodnes of the / yf thou geue it them / then ſhall they gather it: yf thou open thy hande all ſhall be fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with plenty / when thou turneſt away thy face / then are they aſtonyed: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou gathereſt in theyr breth then are they dead and returne in to erthe. And agayne when thou brethedſt on them / then are they crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted anew: and thus renueſt thou the face of the earth Pſalme .C. iiij. Lorde I praye the what profyt is there in the dampnacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſo many thouſande men: Hell is fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and thy churche doth daylye decreaſe. Aryſe Lorde / why ſleapeſt thou ſo longe? Aryſe / and dyffer not vnto the ende / Deale gently of thy fauourable beneuole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with Syon / that the walles of Ieruſalem may be buylded agayne / what is Ieruſalem (whiche by interpretacyon ſignyfyeth the vyſyon of peace) but the holye congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon and cytye of the bleſſed whiche is our
<pb facs="tcp:7177:29"/>mother? Her walles were decayed when Lucyfer with his aungels fel / in to whoſe places are the ryghtwyſe men receyued. Deale therfore gentlye (Oh Lorde) with Syon / that the numbre of thy choſen may ſhortlye be fulfylled / and that the walles of Ieruſalem may be edefied and fyniſſhed with newe ſtones whiche ſhal euer prayſe the and endure euerlaſtynglye.</p>
            <p>Then ſhalte thou accepte the ſacryfyce of ryghtwyſnes / oblacyons and brente offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynges: then ſhall they laye vpon thyne altare wanton calues.</p>
            <p>¶ When thou haſte delt gentlye of thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable will &amp; beneuolence with Syon / then ſhalte thou accepte the ſacryfyce of ryghtwyſnes / for thou ſhalte conſume it with burnyng fier of thy loue and charite / &amp; ſo acceptedſt thou the ſacrifices of Woy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Helyas. And then accepteſt thou the ſacryfices of ryghtwyſnes / when thou fatteneſt with thy grace the ſoules whiche endeuoure them ſelues to lyne rightwiſly. What profiteth to offer ſacryfices vnto the when thou accepteſt them not oh Lorde? Howe manye ſacryfyces offer we nowe a dayes whiche are not pleaſaunt vnto the but rather abhomynable? for we offre not the ſacryfyces of ryghtwyſnes / but oure owne ceremonyes: and therfore are they
<pb facs="tcp:7177:30"/>not accepted, nor regarded of the, where is nowe the glorye of the Apoſtles? where is the valyaunt perſeueraunce of martyrs? where is the frute of preachers? where is that holye ſymplicyte of them that vſed to lyue ſolitarye? where are now the vertues and workes of the chriſten whiche were in olde tyme? Then ſhalt thou excepte theyr ſacryfices / when thou ſhalt decke and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhe them with thy grace and vertues.</p>
            <p>¶ Alſo yf thou deale gently with Syon of thy fauourable beneuolence / then ſhalte thou delyght in ſacryfyces of ryghtwiſnes / for the people ſhall begynne to lyue well / to kepe thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes and to deale iuſtlye and ſo ſhall thy people be endued with thy benefytes and bleſſynge. Then ſhall the oblacyons of the preeſtes and of the clargie be acceptable vnto the / for they ſhall forſake theyr carnal affection and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoure them ſelues vnto a more perfeyte lyfe / and ſo ſhall the oyntment of thy blyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge deſcende vpon theyr heades. Then ſhall the brente offerynges of the relygy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous be pleaſaunte to the / for they ſhal caſt out all drouſye ſluggyſhnes and falſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fydence / and be hooly enflamed and made perfayte with the burnynge fyer of goddes loue. Then ſhall the byſſhoppes and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers put calues vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thyn altare / for after
<pb facs="tcp:7177:30"/>they at co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſummate in al kynde of vertue &amp; replenyſſhed with the holye ſpiryte / they ſhal not feare to geue theyr lyues for theyr ſheepe. What is thyne altare ſwete Ieſu / but thy croſſe where vpon thou waſt offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red? What ſignifyeth a want on calfe / but our bodye? Therfore / then ſhall they put calues on thyne altare / when they ſhal of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer their owne bodies vnto the croſſe / that is, vnto all afflyctions and euen vnto the verye deathe for thy names ſake.</p>
            <p>¶ Then ſhall the churche flory ſhe and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late her cooſtes / then ſhall thy prayſe be noyſed from the laſte ende of the worlde / then ſhal ioye and gladnes fulfyll the hole worlde. Then ſhall thy ſayntes reioyce in glorye and ſhal make myrth in theyr man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyons waytynge for vs in the londe of the lyuynge. Accomplyſhe in me euen nowe Lorde that / then / whiche I ſo ofte name that thou mayſte haue compaſſion on me accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to thy great mercy / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thou mayſt receyue me for a ſacryfice of ryghtwyſnes / for a holy oblacyon: for a brente ſacryfyce of good lyuynge / and for a calfe to be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on thyne altare or croſſe / by the which</p>
            <p>I maye paſſe from this vale of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerye vnto that ioye whiche thou haſt prepared for them that loue the.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="exposition">
            <pb facs="tcp:7177:31"/>
            <head>¶ To fyll vp the lefe we haue touched cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne places whiche we thought moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to edefye the congregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of faythe.</head>
               <p>FIrſt dere dretherne ye ought to geue dylygent hede that you maye pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye vnderſtonde what faythe is and what frutes procede out of her / And to conclude the ſumme in fewe wordes / fayth is a ſure perſwaſyon and full knowlege that god for his truthe and ryghtwyſnes ſake wyll fulfyll ſuche promyſes / as he hathe made vnto vs of his mercye and fauoure / which ſure perſwaſion muſt be geuen from god. i. Corin .xij. For it can neither be goten by mannes power / nether yet retayned / ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with feare and tremblynge performe that helthe whiche is begonne in you / for it is god that worketh in you both the wil and alſo the dede / euen at his owne plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. And ſe that with all mekenes ye ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myt your ſelues vnto the vocacion of god / not ſeking the lyberty of the fleſhe / nether yet deſpyſyng good workes / for faith doth mortefye the fleſhe and her workes / &amp; the ſpirite of god whiche reſteth in a faythfull man helpeth our inſurmitie and fyghteth without intermiſſion agaynſte ſynne / the deuyll and the worlde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:7177:31"/>
               <head>¶ The power of faythe.</head>
               <p>THe power of fayth is to iuſtefye vs: that is / to diſpoyle vs frome all our vices and laye them on Chriſtꝭ backe whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che hathe pacefyed the fathers wrathe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs: and to endue vs with an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ryhtwyſnes / that is Chriſtꝭ / ſo that I and all my ſynnes are Chriſtes / &amp; Chriſt with all his vertues are myne / for he was borne for vs and geuen vnto vs. Eſaye. ix. Roma .viii. To obteyne this ryghtwiſnes god the father requireth nothing of vs but that we beleue in hym and make hym no lyar. He that beleueth that god of his mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cye hath made vs theſe promiſes &amp; that for his truthes ſake he wil fulfyl them / he ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to his ſeale y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god is true. But he that beleueth not or doubteth of this (as much as in him is) he maketh him a liar .i. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> v. for why ſholdeſt thou doubte in hym ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte thou thoughteſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he were a lyar &amp; wold not kepe his pro;meſſe which he made? Now yf thou counte God (whiche is the verye truthe) to be a lyar / arte thou not worthye a thouſande dampnacyones.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The worke of faythe.</head>
               <p>FAyth worketh by charite / for when my ragyng conſcience which fealeth her ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e is pacefied &amp; ſet at one with God
<pb facs="tcp:7177:32"/>thrughe fayth / then remembrynge the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent loue of god towardes me I can not but loue my neyghboure agayne / for there is no man that hertelye loueth the father and can hate the ſone / and althoughe the ſonne be naught and vnthriftye yet for his fathers ſake he wyll helpe to better hym and euen lament and be ſorye for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonnes wyckedneſſe. Lykewyſe yf we hertely loue god for his infinyte benefytes done vnto vs / then can we not hate y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> creature which he hath made after his own lykenes / who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god the father loueth ſo tenderly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he gaue his owne ſonne vnto the death to redeme him / yea &amp; whom he hath adopted (thrugh Chriſte) to be his ſonne and heyre. Nowe all be it we ſe no kyndenes in this man for whiche we ſholde loue hym yet hath god ſhewed vs kyndnes ynough for the which we ought to loue hym &amp; ſo coure hym at al tymes. Let vs therfore loue hym for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue that god his creatoure hathe ſhewed vs / &amp; beare his infyrmitye / yf he faule let vs lyft hym vp agayne / and endue hym with our myſdome &amp; all our workes euen as Chriſt hath done with vs / and this is an euydent token that thou loueſt god / when thou lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueſt thy brother .i. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .iiij. and ſeakeſt al meanes to helpe hym / theſe are the good workes that folow fayth / and are euydent
<pb facs="tcp:7177:32"/>tokens that thy faythe is ryght and pure. Thus ſeeſt thou how good workes / flowe out of faythe through charite / &amp; charite or loue is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fulfilling of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hole lawe. Ro .xiij.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Good workes.</head>
               <p>AMonge good workes the chyef are: to be obedyente in all thynges vnto kynges / prynces / Iudges / and ſuche other offycers as farre as they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde ciuyle thynges that is to ſay ſuch thynges as are indyfferente / and not contrarye vnto the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of god / for then muſt we rather obaye God then men / actes in the fyrſt chapitre although we ſhold leſe both our ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and lyfe therto: To honour rulers: To promote peace: To praye for all comynaltyes. And to applye al our ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes to profyte them.</p>
               <p>¶ The nexte are: to be obedyent vnto fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; mother: To prouyde for our houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde both nouryſhyng our famylye with bodelye ſuſtenaunce / and alſo to enſtructe them with the worde of god / and ſo to be theyr gouernour carnall and ſpirituall.</p>
               <p>¶ Then muſte we loke howe we oughte to behaue our ſelues towardes our neygh boures knowlegynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al the gyftꝭ which are geuen vs of god / are not geuen vs for our owne ſelfe but for the edefyenge of the
<pb facs="tcp:7177:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .j. Corynth .xij. &amp; yf we beſtow them not on that maner we ſhall ſurelye geue a rekenyng for them before the lorde. Emonge theſe ought we to haue reſpecte vnto the preachers and myneſters of the worde / that they maye be had in honoure and well prouyded for. And aboue all thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges good bretherne addreſſe your ſelues vnto that neceſſary worke prayer. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre to praye for all eſtates / for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is a worke that Chryſt &amp; his apoſtles full dylygently exhorted all men vnto / promyſynge them that they ſholde obtayne theyr perycyons Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xvj. alſo .j. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .iij. yf they be accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to the wyll of god and for his glorye .j. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .v.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Here endeth the expoſition vpon the lj. Pſalme called Miſerece meidens. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prented at Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Flete ſtrete by Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Byddeii / dwellynge next to Flete brydge at the ſygne of our lady of pytye / for wyllyam Marſhall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio Regali.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7177:33"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
